Guide to the Emma Goldman Papers, 1909-1941 and undated RL.11353
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1909-1941 and undated; 1
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (Willesden, England), [1924 December 28]; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman requests the name of the publisher of a recent book on Syndicalism. She then discusses the review and advertising for her book in Freedom.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 February 3; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman makes requests for an estimate to produce a magazine and for pamphlets, both on behalf of students with which she has contact.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 February 5; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes of the indifference she is facing regarding her tour of England; no anarchists have stepped up to assist. She then asks for background regarding a comrade who has worked in the movement but is now down and out.
    Anarchism -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 February 8; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman thanks Keell for possible contacts for her tour of England and Scotland, and discusses Glasgow in particular. She then orders sets of pamphlets for her students, and mentions two halls they may get for the tour.
    Anarchism -- Great Britain; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 February 23; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman expresses shock about the cost Keell must have incurred for a shipment of publications from New York, some of which she did not want. She then discusses possible tour dates, and requests his help firming up the schedule.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), [1925] February 24; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman plans her response to a Socialist report on Russia that appeared in the newspapers, which she hopes to publish in article or pamphlet form. She then points out that their "deportation" pamphlet is sorely out of date and cannot be used. She closes by noting conflicts in her touring schedule.
    Socialism -- Soviet Union; Anarchism -- Great Britain; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (Willesden, England), 1925 March 3; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman comments on a comrade who has confused his stand on Russia, then orders a rubber stamp.
    Anarchism -- Soviet Union; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), [1925 March 13]; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes regarding plans for an independent meeting to be held in Northampton, and publications she would like for the meeting. In a postscript, she requests a copy of a paper.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 March 17; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman reports on her lecture at Northampton. She then outlines changes in her tour dates, and alterations in her needs for publications as a result. She ends the letter by discussing the misreporting of a speech made by a mutual friend.
  - Emma Goldman (Treherbert, Wales) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 March 31; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests a copy of her Essays for a reader, then requests information on the "'United Front' of the Moscow gang, and the English Trade Unions" for a speech.
    Politicians -- Soviet Union; Labor Unions -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Treherbert, Wales) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 April 2; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests a copy of Freedom, so that John Turner may comment on an article she wrote.
  - Emma Goldman (no place) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1925 April 6; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman thanks Keell for the material she requested, although it is not enough for a lecture. She reports that they have had tussles with Communists, especially those that have been drinking.
    Communists -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (no place) to Tom [Keell] (Willesden, England), 1925 April 9; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests a copy of the Daily Herald for a pamphlet she is writing, then asks him to confirm the amount of literature ordered for Norwich.
    Daily herald (London, England); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 April 23; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman reports that her latest meeting "was a frost, hardly a hundred people and a spiritless crowd." She points out how painful the process of even bringing people together has been. She then requests books for her own reading, and orders literature for her Manchester meeting.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 April 27; 2 Leaves; 4 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman outlines corrections to be printed in Freedom for their latest pamphlet.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 May 5; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 17 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman asks for 50 copies of their pamphlet, and corrections slips for the 2,800 pamphlets they have printed.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 May 8; 1 Leaves; 1 page: 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman asks about a contact for an Edinburgh University student, requests copies of their pamphlet, with more for the newspaper exchanges. She notes Berkman will cover the Russian papers in Berlin.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 May 8; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman notes that they cannot afford the expense of reproducing their report; printing will be cheaper, and she asks Keell to take over the order for the report and financial statement. She then announces she will have tickets to a piano recital, if Keell and his family wish to attend.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 May 11; 4 Leaves; 5 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman bemoans the fact that they have no one to help with their work "or to really care a damn about it." She then reviews the plan for printing the report and their financial statement and for mailing all of it with their pamphlet. She then goes over orders for the pamphlet that have come from New York, debating their cost, which is to be determined.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 May 14; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests a stamp with publisher Boni Liveright's name so that she can stamp Alexander Berkman's folders.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 May 18; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests that pamphlets be mailed to a contact in Washington, D.C., to be put on sale with trade unionists. She then asks how they stand in their accounts. She plans to advertise Berkman's Memoirs and her Essays together. She announces that a discounted version of her volumes on Russia will soon be produced, but she will have to borrow the money to cover her part in the expenses.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 June 16; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman asks Keell to arrange meetings between Pierre Ramus and Jewish and English comrades. She offers to preside, if that helps attendance. She also asks him to attend a ceremony and to house a friend coming to town.
    Anarchism -- Great Britain; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Ramus, Pierre.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 June 19; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 17 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that James? Colton plans to visit. She then describes her feelings about an unidentified ceremony and requests a book from Keell.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 July 13; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman outlines a circular for her lectures on modern drama she wishes Keell to arrange for her. She adds that she wishes Freedom were not so hard pressed, and that she hopes to help through her general propaganda work.
    Drama; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Bristol, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 July 17; 4 Leaves; 7 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Keell has sent a proof for Goldman's requested circular, and she provides corrections. She then states that she is exhausted from her 10 month's work, and she is taking a week off in Bristol. She advises him to write to Alexander Berkman for copies of his book. She closes with a promise to write a future article on the closing of the Russian Solovetsky concentration camp for political prisoners.
    Drama; Solovetski Islands (Russia); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 August 11; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman asks for a missing volume of Mother Earth, then discusses the availability of Berkman's book and a reduced rate for the American edition of her set on Russia. She expresses dismay at the public announcement of her change of names. She closes by mentioning a committee meeting.
    Mother earth (New York, N.Y.: Online); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 September 1; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman enquires about the costs for engraving a card and letterhead for stationary to be used for the drama lectures.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 September 8; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman orders another 1000 copies of her circular, then checks on the status of her visiting card.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 September 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman includes a new final paragraph for her circular, and asks again about the proof for her visiting card. She mentions a speaking engagement by [Herman?] Sandomirsky.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 September 26; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman orders several books for her own reading, and asks Keell to find out if publishers will supply books to sell at her meetings, and whether they have published Russian plays. She says that the work done in Bristol has been very encouraging, then outlines other engagements, including a drama lecture on O'Neill. She hopes her work on drama will provide her with a living that will support her work on other ideas and the Russian situation.
    Anarchism -- Great Britain; Drama; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 October 7; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman outlines her debts, particularly in regard to a printer, and worries about how she will pay them.
    Debt; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 October 14; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman sends payment for a book, then orders other publications. She mentions that she is leaving copies of Myth on her shelves in case Keell has orders for them.
  - Emma Goldman (Bristol, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 October 20; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests a correct address for Pierre Ramus. She reports that her recent meeting was well attended, although her drama lecture was not.
  - Emma Goldman (Bristol, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 October 26; 6 Leaves; 9 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that there is evidence that the Russians are "trying to break up the last oasis of the anarchists," the Kropotkin Museum. She cautions against publishing the news in Freedom, until there is confirmation. She points out that the Russians have already had success in separating the ranks of anarchist refugees. She then reports low attendance for her drama lectures. She has "lost hope" and feels depressed. In contrast, her recent political meetings have been packed, with responsive and attentive listeners, and she has an additional lecture upcoming. She goes on to outline what literature is selling at her meetings. She worries about plans for a lecture at Keat's house, then offers Keell a complimentary ticket to a lecture. She hopes to soon have money to pay her debts.
    Anarchism -- Soviet Union; Anarchism -- Great Britain; Debt; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 November 11; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman points out that she has a check to cover her printer's debt. She orders several books for her own use. She writes that she has too many Bulletins, and states "I wish I knew what the Committee could do to arrange a meeting or something, it is awful to know the continued percecution [sic] in Russia and to be unable to help...." She asks Keell if he has any pamphlets containing methods of birth control for an upcoming lecture on the topic. In a postscript, she comments on her 33rd anniversary in the movement.
    Debt; Freedom bulletin (London, England); Birth control -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (Willesden, England), 1925 November 20; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman states that the pamphlet on birth control Keell obtained only describes one method, and wonders what the Margaret Sanger pamphlet does.
    Birth control -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 December 4; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman announces that she is going away for 8-10 weeks, and has material to return to Keell, as well as items to discuss. She adds that Harry Kelly will soon be arriving from the United States, and outlines plans to meet his train and arrange a social for him.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Kelly, Harry, 1871-1953
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 December 11; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman sends copy for Freedom and requests some plays. She outlines plans to meet with the Committee so that she can leave things in order before she leaves.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1925 [No date]; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman asks Keell to obtain the lease for her books and newspaper clippings from Germany. She will send copy to accompany Berkman's book.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 February 14; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that she has been alternately relaxing and working, writing an article on [Johann?} Most and a series of drama lectures on Ibsen. She adds that "I only feel disgusted that we play no part whatever in the awakening of the masses." She cannot arrange for drama lectures, let alone political meetings. Goldman orders more books for her use, then mentions that they should send Berkman's book to Dr. Paolo Flores for translation into Italian, and points to another book of documents compiled by Berkman that should be advertised in Freedom.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Ibsen, Henrik, 1828-1906
  - Emma Goldman (Bristol, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 March 11; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that she has been lecturing despite being ill, and has found new rooms, although she plans to return to France to work on a manuscript of Russian plays. She orders more books for her use. She notes that a representative of the publisher has been able to quickly sell copies of Myth; in contrast, she has been able to sell only a few.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 March 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that the first edition of the Myth has sold out and she has enquired about a second edition. She also requests several books in support of her Russian drama lectures. She reports that attendance was low at the last lecture, and she will discontinue them if attendance does not improve.
    Russian drama; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 April 11; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman announces that she has called for a Committee meeting. She attempts to set up a meeting for Keell and Ben? Reitman.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1926 April 29; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman makes plans for a meeting with Keell.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 May 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman plans to fly to Paris now that the General Strike is occurring. She had hoped to have a part in the strike, but was told they had enough help for the present. She gives her addresses, then requests that Keell send her Freedom, along with other publications about the strike.
    Strikes and lockouts -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 May 19; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes about the general strike, and her feeling that it is easy to be critical after the fact. She requests several books for her use, along with a review copy of "Love Letters of an Archivist."
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 June 4; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes about the "indifference of those who call themselves comrades," the failure of anarchists to play a leading role in the recent general strike, and the man who killed Petlura. She states she cannot finish "Love Letters of an Archivist," let alone review it.
    Strikes and lockouts -- England; Anarchism -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 June 9; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman makes note of a comrade who wishes not to be known as an anarchist. She outlines plans for lectures in Canada and requests information.
    Anarchism -- Canada; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 June 17; 2 Leaves; 4 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that she has begun work on her Russian drama manuscript, then thanks Keell for obtaining her books, while requesting more. She then discusses plans for her sailing to Canada.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 July 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that she has completed an article on the general strike, and encloses a copy which she would like returned if Keell does not publish it in Freedom. She requests more copies of Cook's pamphlet on the strike, then outlines a planned visit with George Davison. She discusses Freedom's struggle to continue publishing and the general state of the movement in England.
    Strikes and lockouts -- England; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Davison, George, 1854-1930
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 July 17; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman orders more books for her own use and requests an invoice for all of her book orders.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 August 3; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests more books, then describes a visit she and Berkman made with George and Joan Davison.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Davison, George, 1854-1930
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 August 20; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman writes that she has received the books Keell sent. She comments on the British edition of Berkman's Memoirs, then asks for the latest date she may submit an article to Freedom. She outlines her planned trip to Canada, then worries about the possibility that the trip will fall through. She comments on George Davison's lack of interest in anarchist affairs, despite his former activity.
    Anarchism -- Canada; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Davison, George, 1854-1930
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 August 31; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman reports that her Canada trip seems more certain, and outlines plans and travel dates. She then orders several books, and comments on Keell's devotion to the cause and printing of Freedom.
    Anarchism -- Canada; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 September 11; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman submits her article on Keell's work with Freedom.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 September 16; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman pays her debts and makes a contribution to Freedom, then discusses the articles for the newspaper and her packing for her trip to Canada.
    Debt; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 September 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman supplies her address in Canada and requests that Keell mail Freedom there. She notes that she does not plan to cross into the United States; anyone who wishes to see her must come to her. She adds some final details about her plans.
  - Emma Goldman (Cherbourg, France) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1926 October 7?; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman sends greetings at the beginning of her voyage.
  - Emma Goldman (Montreal, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 October 23; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman states that she has arrived safely, but is uncertain whether she will be permitted to stay, despite assurances to the contrary. An "English meeting" has been arranged for her by the Peoples Forum. She adds that there has been much publicity, but that "her marriage" is what interests people the most. She requests copies of publications be mailed to her.
    Anarchists -- Canada; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Montreal, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 November 25; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman sends money for Freedom and for copies of the publication. She then reports on her meetings, in which she has not been disappointed, despite their small size.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Anarchism -- Canada; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 November 29; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman requests copies of the anniversary issue of Freedom, along with other publications.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1926 December 23; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 35 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Goldman settles accounts, then mentions that she was given a surprise party to commemorate her deportation 7 years ago. She used the occasion to raise money for Freedom. She requests other literature. She comments on her marriage, which means no more to her than a visa.